Now that we can destroy our hazards
现在我们可以消灭小行星
we should reward our player with points.
我应该用得分来奖励我们的玩家
Let's count and display a score
让我们计算并显示一下得分
where every asteroid hazard destroyed
击毁一个小行星给予
gives our player 10 points.
玩家10分
We will start by creating a display for the score
在我们知道如何计算得分之前
before we create a score value to feed it with.
让我们先研究一下如何显示得分
First using the Create menu
首先在层级视图点选Create菜单并选择GUI Text
in the Hierarchy view select GUI Text.
(5.0以后的版本请选择UI -> Text代替GUI Text)
This creates a new game object with
这样就新建出了一个附带了
a GUI text component attached.
GUI text组建的对象(5.0以后用text代替GUI Text)
Rename this game object Score Text.
把这个对象重命名为Score Text
We can now see GUI text being
我们现在可以看到GUI text
displayed in the centre of our game area.
在游戏的中心区域显示了
The Text property on the GUI text component
GUI text组件的文本属性
drives what is being displayed.
决定了显示的内容
The rest of the component describes
其他的组建描述了
how this text is displayed and where this
这个文本是如何显示的
text is displayed on screen.
和在屏幕的什么位置显示
We will not go in to all of the details
我们这里不详细描述
of the GUI text component.
GUI text组建的细节
For more information on GUI text
GUI text的更多详细信息
see the details linked below.
请查看下方链接
In later assignments we will create
在后面的任务中
additional GUI text objects
我们会建立GUI text对象
to hold different information.
来保存不同的信息
With the default GUI text in the Text property
如果使用默认的GUI text的Text属性
on all of them the Game View at edit time
在游戏场景视图中会显得
could become a little confusing.
很混乱(因为显示出来的名称都相同)
Change the Text property to Score Text.
把Text属性改名为Score Text
We can see Score Text is now being
我们看到Score Text已经
displayed in the Game View.
显示在了游戏视图中了
We will be changing this value at runtime.
这个值会实时的变化
Changing this label now will help
我们将这个标签改成了这个新名字
us identify which display is which while editing.
这样我们更容易定位我们正在编辑的是哪个文本的显示
Our Score Text is currently displaying
Score Text是现在显示在
in the middle of our screen.
屏幕正中的那个
Let's move it so it displayed in the upper
让我们把它移动到
left of the game screen.
屏幕的左上角
Before we change any settings
在更改设定之前
it's important to understand
我们首先要了解
that GUI text is drawn on a layer
GUI text是画在游戏之上的层上的
above our game, not in the game world.
它并不在游戏中绘制
We won't see it in our Scene view.
所以场景视图中看不到这些文本
Moreover it is important to understand
并且我们需要理解
that the GUI text uses something called
GUI text使用的是视图空间
Viewport Space, rather than screen space.
而不是屏幕空间
The difference, very briefly,
简单的说一下不同就是
is that screen space is defined in pixels.
屏幕空间是由像素决定的
This is the number of pixels wide
就是指屏幕的长宽
and high that we set in our player settings.
分别有多少像素是由我们设定的
Viewport Space is defined simply
视图空间是一种更简单的设定
as a single width and height value
它的长宽表示为
with (0 0) in the lower left
左下角为(0 0)
and (1,1) in the upper right.
右上角是(1,1)
With Viewport Space in mind
掌握了视图空间
set the transform position on the display text
我们就清楚了X Y的设定如果是(0.5, 0.5)
from (0.5, 0.5) on the X and Y,
那么显示就在正中间
in other words the middle of the screen,
也就是屏幕的正中间
to (0, 1), which is the upper left.
如果让它显示在左上角就设置为(0, 1)
The text seems wedged up against
这个文本似乎贴在了
the upper left corner.
左上角
It would be good to give it some pad
如果这个文本与屏幕的
or space around it to separate
边界有一定的空隙或者空间的话
it from the edges of t he game screen.
那就是最好的了
Because of the viewport space
如果在视图空间
it is awkward trying to set such a small
设定一个很小的值
value of space using the transform component.
是一个不怎么有效的操作
This solution to this is to use pixel offset.
解决这个问题的方法就是使用像素补偿
Pixel offset is, not too surprisingly,
像素补偿很直观的就是
using pixels.
使用像素
So we can set our primary location
因此我们可以先用空间视图的值
with the transform component,
设定一个大概的位置
the upper left corner,
例如左上角
and then perfect it with pixel offset.
然后用像素补偿完善具体位置
Change Pixel Offset to 10 and -10.
将像素补偿的值设定为10 和 -10
This will give us a 10 pixel
这样我们的分数显示文本周边
pad around our score text.
就有了10个像素的空间
Separating it from the edge of the screen.
这样就跟屏幕的变分开了
Next we need to feed Score Text
下一步我们要将分数文本
a score value.
填充上分数
Select Game Controller and open the
点击打开GameController脚本
GameController script for editing.
并编辑
The first thing we need is a
我们首先需要做的是
public GUI Text variable called scoreText
声明一个公有的GUI Text变量命名为scoreText
to hold a reference to our GUI text component.
来保存对GUI text组件的引用
The next thing we need is a
下一步需要做的是
public int variable called score
建一个公有的变量命名为score
to hold our current score.
来保存现在的得分
We use int because we will never count
我们使用整数是因为
a partial point.
这个值从来都不是分数
Score will always be a whole number.
总是一个整数
Our game controller will keep track
游戏控制脚本会一直追踪
of our score, increment it when we destroy hazards
这个得分,在击毁小行星的时候加分
and feed that value to our score text.
并显示到我们的得分显示区域
To update our score we need to write a new function.
为了不停的更新我们的得分我们得写个新的函数
Write void update score.
敲入代码void updatescore()
And the code within this function is
这个函数中的代码是
scoreText.text = "score: " +score.
scoreText.text = "score: " +score
This function will set the text property
这个函数会设置Score Text组件的
on the Score Text component
文本属性为
to the string Score: plus whatever our
字符串Score:加
current score value is held by our score variable.
我们当前score这个变量中的值
When written like this Unity automatically
当我们这样写这段代码Unity会自动的将
converts the int value of Score
这个整型的值Score
to a string of text characters
转换成为字符串的形式
so it works with our text property.
这样就可以复合我们的文本属性
This feeds our score value
这样我们就可以把score的值
to our GUI text component.
填写到GUI text组件当中
We next need to update our score
下一步是在两处更新
in two different places.
我们的score值
When we first start the game
分别是游戏开始的时候
and when a hazard is destroyed.
和小行星被击毁的时候
When we start the game the first thing we need
当我们开始游戏的时候
to do is set our score to 0.
我们得把score设定为0
Then we want to call update Score
然后我们调用updateScore函数
to set the score text to this starting value.
把分数文本设定成这个初始值
Now how can we tell from inside Game Controller
现在的问题是我们怎么在GameController内部
when a hazard has been destroyed by the player?
得知一个小行星被玩家机会了?
Well, we can't.
恩,我们做不到
But we can expose a public function
但是我们可以为
to the other game objects in our game
其他游戏对象开发一个公共函数
like the hazards themselves
例如小行星
and when they are destroyed the hazards
当小行星被击毁了
can inform Game Controller to add to the score,
它们可以通知GameController增加分数
and the Game Controller can use this information
GameController可以把这个信息
as a signal to update the score text.
作为更新得分文本的信号
Let's create a public function for our hazards.
让我们为小行星建个公共函数
Write public void AddScore
敲入代码void AddScore
with the parameter int newScoreValue.
带newScoreValue这个变量
First we write code to update our score value
首先敲入更新得分的代码
with score += newScoreValue.
score += newScoreValue
And then we call the function UpdateScore
然后我们调用UpdateScore函数
to update our score text to display
来吧我们显示的得分
the new current score.
更新成新的分数
We now need to call Add Score
现在我们需要在
from our game when a hazard is destroyed.
小行星被击毁的时候调用AddScore函数
Save this script and switch back to Unity.
保存当前脚本切换回Unity
Let's look at our asteroid hazards
让我们看看小行星这个对象
We want our instances of this prefab
我们希望小行星预制件
to call addScore on GameController
在被玩家击毁的时候
when they are destroyed by the player.
调用addScore这个函数
The player destroys our hazards through the
玩家击毁小行星
DestroyByContact script.
是通过脚本DestroyByContact
So open DestroyByContact for editing.
因此打开DestroyByContact并编辑
First let's give our hazards a value
首先给我们的小行星
with public int scoreValue.
一个公有的整形变量scoreValue
Now how do we call a function
我们如何调用另一个游戏对象
on another component on a different game object?
的组建的函数呢?
We can try to access this by writing
让我们试试写代码
GameController.AddScore
and then send the new score value
然后我们把刚建好的score value
with the argument scoreValue.
作为scoreValue这个参数
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
Well we seem to have an error.
现在报错了
We can see the most recent error in the footer.
我们可以通过脚标看到最新的报错
Let's open the console and look at this
让我们把控制台打开
error more closely.
仔细看一下这个报错
The error seems to be on the script
这个报错时关于
we have just edited, not surprisingly,
我们刚编辑的脚本DestroyByContact
the DestroyByContact script.
果然不出所料
This error says
报错的内容是
an object reference is required to access
需要一个对象的引用来保证
non-static member GameController.AddScore(int).
非静态参数GameController.AddScore(int)的可达
Why is this?
为什么是这个报错?
This is because we are addressing the
这是因为
class directly, not a specific
我们直接引用了这个类
instance of our class.
而不是这个类的一个实例
If we look at our Game Controller object
我们看一下Game Controller对象
we can see that there is a GameController
它上面附加了GameController
script attached.
脚本
This is an instance of this script or class.
这是这个脚本或者类的实例
This is very much like all of the asteroid
这个实例化就像小行星
hazards or laser bolts that we have
镭射子弹那样
instantiated in our scene.
在场景中实例化
Each one is an instance.
每个都是一个实例
Even though we have one and only one
虽然我们的游戏中
GameController script in our game
仅有一个GameController脚本的实例
there is nothing technically stopping us
但是技术上我们是可以
from having several.
产生GameController脚本的很多个实例
If we created a new game object,
如果我们新建一个对象
say a cube, there is nothing stopping
例如一个立方体,没什么可以阻止我们
us from having another instance of
在这个立方体上实例化
GameController on it.
GameController
Now we have two instances of our
现在我们实例化了
GameController script.
两个GameController的脚本
When our hazard is destroyed it needs to know
当我们的小行星被击毁了
which one to call AddScore on.
它需要知道调用哪个实例的脚本来加分
This is very much like valet parking.
这就好比我们叫侍者帮助泊车
We can't simply say
我们不能简单的只说
'please, can you bring our car?'.
‘请帮忙把我们的车开过来’
We must have a reference to a specific car,
我们必须有一个指向特定车的引用
usually through a numbered ticket
通常来说是个号码标签卡
so the valet knows which one to bring.
这样侍者就知道把哪辆车开过来了
Let's delete our example cube.
让我们把我们例子立方体删除
Even though we have only one instance
虽然我们只实例化了一个GameController脚本
we still need a reference to it.
我们依旧需要一个对它的引用
That valet won't bring our car without a ticket,
如果我们没标签卡侍者不会把车开给我们
even if it's the only one on the lot.
即使停车场只有一辆车
Reopen DestroyByContact for editing.
重新打开并编辑DestroyByContact
Let's write a variable to hold our
让我们写一个变量来保存
reference to our instance of GameController.
我们实例化的GameController的引用
Write public GameController gameController
写下public GameController gameController
Note the 2 different capitalisation's.
注意这2个单词的首字母大小写
The first Game Controller with a capital G
第一个GameController的首字母G大写
is the class name, or type.
因为它是类名称或者类型名称
The second Game Controller with the lower case g
第二个gameController首字母g小写
is the name of our variable.
它是变量名称
Now if we copy and paste the
然后我们在把变量的名称
name of our variable in to the
复制粘贴到
offending line of code we change the line from
结尾的代码中
addressing the class directly
我们把直接使用类
to using the reference to our instance
改为使用一个保存了
that we have held in our variable.
实例的索引
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本并回到Unity
And the error is gone.
报错不见了
Let's switch to the Game View.
让我们切换回游戏视图
Select the Asteroid prefab.
点选小行星预制件
We can now see the Game Controller
我们现在可以看到在DestroyByContact
type reference on the DestroyByContact component.
脚本组建处有一个Game Controller类型的引用槽
We need to associate our instance of
我们需要把实例化的GameController
GameController with this variable.
与这个变量做一个链接
So let's drag our GameController object
让我们把GameController对象
on to the slot to make the reference.
拖拽到这个槽位形成一个引用
Okay, that doesn't work.
似乎不能这么用
Let's try to use the asset picker.
让我们再试一下资源选择器
Nope.
也不行
This is not working.
我们无法这么做
Why?
为什么呢？
This comes back to the nature of instances.
这里要回过来谈谈实例的本质
Instances are copies of objects within a scene.
实例是场景中对象的一个副本
Now if we think about the nature of prefabs,
再来说一下预制件的本质
prefabs are templates of game objects
预制件是游戏对象的一个模版
that can be instantiated in any scene in our game.
这个模版可以在游戏内的任何场景中被实例化
It doesn't make sense that a template
但这听起来并不合理
that can be added to any scene in our game
一个可以被添加到游戏中任何场景的模版
can hold a reference to an instance
可以保存的实例化对象的引用
in just one scene.
仅仅只在一个场景中
Now once we have instantiated our
当我们在场景中
hazards in to the scene
实例化了一个小行星
and we have an instance of our hazard
这个实例化的小行星
these instances can hold a reference
保留了一个实例化的GameController
to our instance of the Game Controller.
的引用
So we have to find our references
所以我们需要在游戏开始的时候
to the Game Controller after the game has started.
找到这个GameController的引用
Each new hazard will have to find a new
每个新的小行星在它实例化的时候
reference to Game Controller
都需要找到一个
when they are instantiated.
新的对GameController的引用
Open DestroyByContact for editing.
打开DestroyByContact脚本并编辑
Every hazard has an instance of this script
每个小行星都都有一个这个脚本的实例
and every hazard will have to find
并且小行星都要
their own reference to the Game
找到自己对
Controller component on the Game
GameController对象的
Controller game object.
GameController组建的引用
Let's modify this script to do just that.
让我们把这个脚本修改一下完成上述功能
In Start we first need to find
开始的时候我们需要
the game object that holds
找到保存GameController脚本
our Game Controller script.
的游戏对象
Let's call this reference the
让我们把这个引用起名为
gameControllerObject.
gameControllerObject
We will set this reference by using
我们可以通过
GameObject.FindWithTag
and the tag we will look for is
来设定这个引用
GameController.
需要找的标签是GameController
This will find the first game object in the
这个函数会找到场景中
scene that we have tagged as GameController
的第一个标有GameController标签的对象
and we have only one.
我们这里只有一个标有GameController的对象
Remember we tagged our Game Controller object
回忆一下我们在新建GameController对象的时候
with Game Controller when we created it.
已经给它加上标签了
Next if we have successfully found the
下一步是如果我们
game controller object,
成功找到了GameController对象
and we check this by testing the reference
我们需要通过测试检查一下
to the Game Controller object.
这个对GameController对象的引用
So if the Game Controller object
所以如果GameController对象
is not null
不是null
where null means nothing or empty
这里null的意思是没有或者空的
essentially no reference,
就是本质上说没引用
then we will set our Game Controller
我们就将它设置为
reference to the Game Controller component
对GameController对象的GameController组建
on the Game Controller object.
的引用
We do this by searching the Game Controller
我们是通过搜索GameController对象的
object and getting the component on it,
并通过GetComponent函数获得
with GetComponent.
它的组件来实现上述功能的
searching for the type of GameController.
搜索GameController这个类型
Note this syntax where
注意这里的语法
Game Controller is in angle brackets
GameController使用的是角括号
followed by parenthesis.
后面跟着小括号
Technically this is all the code we need.
技术上说我们需要的代码已经齐了
We are however going to write
我们这里要多写一些
an insurance policy.
来做个保险
If, after all this work,
如果经过上述的代码
our Game Controller reference is
我们的GameController引用
the same as null
还是null
we will use Debug.Log
我们要使用Debug.Log
to put "Cannot find 'GameController' script"
在控制台输出"Cannot find 'GameController' script"
in to the console.
(找不到游戏控制器脚本)
Note that we are using single quotes
注意这里我们在GameController
around GameController so the entire
前后使用了单引号
message is one string of text.
这样这段文字就可以成为一个完整的字符串文本
This is an insurance policy.
这就是我们做的保险
With hope this line of code will never get called.
虽然我们希望这段代码永远都不要被调用
If however something goes wrong
然而如果一旦什么地方出了问题
and we accidentally break something
或者我们意外的弄错了什么
and our game stops working or behaves badly
我们的游戏不能正常运行或者
with messages like these in our console
在控制台出现了这样的错误消息
we will have a place to start.
我们就知道从哪下手来修正了
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
Let's setup our asteroid hazard.
让我们设置一下我们的小行星
Select the Asteroid prefab game object
选择小行星的预制件
and set the Score value to 10.
把得分值设置为10
Below Score Value is the reference
分数值下面是对GameController
to Game Controller.
的引用
We can't set this in the Inspector.
这个并不能通过查看器设定
If we cannot set this in the Inspector
如果我们不能在查看器中设定
let's not see it in the Inspector.
那么我们也别让它在查看器中显示出来
Open DestroyByContact for editing.
打开DestroyByContact脚本并编辑
Change public to private
把GameController的属性由
on the Game Controller reference.
公有改成私有
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存这个脚本回到Unity
Now we have no access to this property
现在在查看器中看不到这个属性了
in the Inspector or from any other
这个属性也无法被其他脚本使用
script, it is private.
因为是私有的
Let's setup our Game Controller.
让我们设置一下我们的GameController
Select Game Controller.
选定GameController
Take note of Score.
看一下这里的Score属性
Unlike the Game Controller reference on the
跟小行星预制件引用GameController不太一样
Asteroid prefab we can set Score in the Inspector,
我们可以在查看器里面设置这个Score属性
we just don't want to.
知识我们不想这么干
Score is handled perfectly well in the script.
Score已经被脚本处理的很好了
This property is set by the script on the
这个属性是脚本在最开始的帧
first frame of the game so let's
的时候就设定了的
set this one to private as well.
所以我们把这个值也设置成私有的
Open the Game Controller for editing.
打开GameController脚本编辑一下
Change score from public to private.
把score由公有变成私有
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
We no longer see, not have access,
现在看不到score
to score.
并且也无法获得score了
Let's set our reference to our Score display.
让我们设定一下score的显示
With GameController selected
选定GameController
drag the Score Text game object
把Score Text对象拖拽到
on to the Score Text property
GameController组建的
on the Game Controller component.
Score Text这个属性上
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
保存场景进入到游戏模式
And now we score 10 points for each
现在击毁每个小行星得10分
asteroid we destroy and the score is
分数显示在
displayed in the upper left.
左上角
Fantastic.
非常棒
Next, in the penultimate assignment,
接下来在倒数第二个任务中
we will learn how to break out of our infinite loop
我们将学习如何中断无限循环
and end the game.
并结束游戏